A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor Joseph Johnson, 1852-1855
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Executive Papers of Governor Joseph Johnson, 1852-1855
The Library of Virginia
44076
7.35 cubic feet (16 boxes)
Virginia Governor (1852-1856: Johnson)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905
Biographical Information
Joseph Johnson was born on 19 December 1785 in Orange County, New York. The second son of Joseph and Abigail Johnson, Johnson relocated to Harrison County, Virginia, now West Virginia, in 1801. He married Sarah (Sally) Smith, daughter of Ephraim Smith, on 16 May 1804. Johnson served as captain of the Harrison Riflemen during the War of 1812. Following the war, Johnson represented Harrison County in the House of Delegates for the sessions 1815-1816, 1818-1819, 1819-1820, and 1821-1822. Elected to the Eighteenth & Nineteenth Congresses, Johnson also served in the House of Representatives from 4 March 1823 to 3 March 1827. Subsequent to an unsuccessful reelection to the Twentieth Congress, Johnson was elected to fill the vacancy in the Twenty-second Congress occasioned by the death of Philip Doddridge in 1832. Johnson returned to Washington as a Jackson Democrat to serve in the Twenty-fourth, Twenty-fifth, Twenty-sixth, & Twenty-ninth Congresses from 4 March 1835 to 3 March 1841 and 4 March 1845 to 3 March 1847. At various times during his tenure in the House of Representatives, Johnson chaired several committees including the Committee on Expenditures on Public Buildings, the Committee on Accounts, and the Committee on Revolutionary Claims. Following his federal service, Johnson again represented Harrison County in the House of Delegates for the session of 1847-1848. In 1850, Johnson was elected as one of the delegates to the Convention of 1850-1851 which established universal white adult male suffrage and provided for the popular election of the governor. During the Convention, Johnson acted as chairman of the essential Committee on Suffrage. As a result of his work in the Convention of 1850-1851, Joseph Johnson became the first popularly elected governor of Virginia on 1 January 1852 defeating Whig candidate Judge George W. Summers. Johnson served one four-year term and retired from public office. Although opposed to secession, Johnson nevertheless supported Virginia & the Confederacy during the Civil War. He died in Bridgeport on 27 February 1877 and was buried in the Old Brick Church Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Joseph Johnson's Executive Papers primarily consist of incoming correspondence during his four-year term as governor from 1 January 1852 until 1 January 1856. The correspondence in this collection relates to a variety of topics including appointments & recommendations for state positions; improvements to Capitol Square; the construction of the Washington Equestrian Statue; the Virginia Penitentiary; slavery; arms and ammunition; the militia; Revolutionary War bounty land claims; banks and banking; resignations; extraditions; state expenses & revenue; elections; and others. In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions from the Virginia Senate & House of Delegates; accounts; oaths; contracts; pardons; proposals; receipts; election returns & certificates; qualifications; lists; proclamations; petitions; reports; appointments; resignations; bonds; commissions; orders; proceedings; opinions; and other sundry items.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Executive Papers of Governor Joseph Johnson, 1852-1855
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Flournoy, H. W., CALENDAR OF VIRGINIA STATE PAPERS, January 1, 1836-April 15, 1869, VOL. XI, Richmond: James E. Goode, Printer, 1893.
Separated Material
Oversized materials have been separated to boxes 14-16.
Contents List
- Executive Papers of Governor Joseph Johnson, 1852-1855., Extent: 16 boxes. (Box 1-16)
  The Governor received correspondence from three main sources: the Federal government, Virginia State government, and governors from other states. Federal government correspondents include the following: Daniel Webster & William L. Marcy, Secretaries of State; William A. Graham, Acting Secretary of the Interior; Alexander H. H. Stuart & Robert McClelland, Secretaries of the Interior; William L. Hodge & P. G. Washington, Acting Secretaries of the Treasury; James Guthrie, Secretary of the Treasury; Jefferson Davis, Secretary of War; James C. Dobbin, Secretary of the Navy; and Linn Boyd, Speaker of the House of Representatives.
  Daniel Webster, Secretary of State, writes regarding the distribution of the "Synoptical Index to the Laws of the United States." Webster also transmits documents of the 2d Session of the 31st Congress and two sets of the Annals of Congress (1852 Apr. 3). William L. Marcy, Webster's successor, requests authentication of a document signed by W. C. Merchant (1853 Dec. 17). Marcy also writes regarding the French Universal Exhibition of 1855 (1854 Sept. 21). On 28 November 1854, Marcy requests information relative to the origin, history, statistics, & medical treatment of Asiatic cholera (1854 Nov. 28). Lastly, Marcy transmits a copy of the report of Col. Jebb on prison discipline in England (1855 Mar. 15).
  Acting Secretary of the Interior, William A. Graham, encloses a letter from Marie Haas, Prefect of Haute-Marne, proposing an agency in Virginia for the cutlers of that department (1852 Apr. 20). Alexander H. H. Stuart, Secretary of the Interior, encloses his official certificate of the number of representatives apportioned to the state of Virginia under the seventh enumeration (1852 Aug. 10). Stuart also writes the governor of his receipt of the deed relinquishing all claim of the state of Virginia to the lands of the Virginia Military Land District in Ohio (1852 Dec. 14). Robert McClelland writes regarding coupons due on James River & Kanawha bonds guaranteed by the state of Virginia held in trust by the Department for the benefit of Indian tribes (1855 Jan. 11). Finally, McClelland writes regarding the U. S. Census (1855 Aug. 2).
  William L. Hodge, Acting Secretary of the Treasury, writes regarding an appropriation of Congress to purchase a site and construct a suitable building for a Custom House, Post Office, Court Rooms, and other offices of the United States at Richmond (1853 Jan. 22). James Guthrie, Secretary of the Treasury, encloses a circular regarding the resolution of the Senate that the treasurer be required to procure the aggregate amount of federal, state, city, railroad, canal, & other corporation bonds, stocks, or other evidence of debt held in Europe (1853 Aug. 9). Guthrie also requests the names & addresses of chief officers of the railroad & canal companies in Virginia (1853 Aug. 9). On several occasions, Guthrie requests statements of Virginia banks (1854 Mar. 8, 25, 29, & Dec. 19). Acting Secretary of the Treasury, P. G. Washington, acknowledges receipt of bank documents sent from Virginia (1854 Apr. 22 & 26).
  As Secretary of War, Jefferson Davis writes regarding the construction of the Washington Aqueduct and the need to purchase land in Virginia for an abutment & quarries for the construction of a dam across the Potomac River (incl. act of Congress) (1854 Jan. 19). James C. Dobbin, Secretary of the Navy, requests a copy of the act ceding jurisdiction to certain lands in the neighborhood of the Navy Hospital grounds at Portsmouth, Virginia (1854 Mar. 6). Lastly, Linn Boyd, Speaker of the House of Representatives, informs Governor Johnson of the death of John F. Snodgrass, member of the 13th Congressional District of Virginia (1854 June 10).
  The majority of correspondence in Joseph Johnson's Executive Papers originates from Virginia State government. Significant correspondents from Virginia State government include Governor Joseph Johnson; William H. Richardson, Adjutant General; Charles Dimmock, Commandant of the Public Guard; Charles S. Morgan, Superintendent of the Penitentiary; Sydney Smith Baxter & Willis P. Bocock, Attorneys General; George W. Munford, Clerk of the House of Delegates; and Robert Johnston & George W. Clutter, Auditors of Public Accounts.
  Governor Joseph Johnson often writes from his home in Bridgeport, Virginia, to George W. Munford, Secretary of the Commonwealth, while away from office to take care of his ill wife. Governor Johnson writes concerning acts passed by the Maryland General Assembly for running & marking the boundary line between Virginia & Maryland (1852 Nov. 20). The governor also writes on the subject of the act of Congress making further provision for the satisfaction of Virginia land warrants including letters of Alexander H. H. Stuart, Secretary of the Interior, act of Congress, & Willis P. Bocock, Attorney General (1852 Nov. 23). In addition, Johnson writes regarding the following topics: the sale or lease of the public lot in the town of Petersburg on which the warehouse is erected (1852 Dec. 11); the decision of a judge in New York to deprive Jonathan Lemmon, a citizen of Virginia, of his slaves (1852 Dec. 17); authority of Thomas H. DeWitt, 1st Clerk, to perform the duties of 2nd Auditor in his absence (1853 Apr. 5); the death of treasurer Robert Butler and the close of all state officers (1853 July 22); his wife's ill health and his delay in returning to Richmond until after the meeting of the Legislature (1853 Nov. 25); and the death of his wife (1853 Dec. 12).
  William H. Richardson, Adjutant General, writes regarding authority to construct a gun house on the court house lot in Alexandria (1852 May 29); deficiencies in the equipment at the Armory (1853 July 7); the application of Capt. Joseph V. Scott for tents, etc., for the Petersburg Grays (1854 May 26); the application of the Petersburg Artillery for aid in building a gun house (1854 Sept. 30); the proposal of Beverley Tucker & Robert Archer for the purchase of certain state arms (1854 Dec. 28); the resolution of the Council to sell the lot in Petersburg appropriated for the purpose of erecting a gun house when the house ceases to be used for military purposes (1855 Mar. 7); and arms & equipment issued to the Young Guard (1855 June 18).
  Charles Dimmock, as Commandant of the Public & Superintendent of Public Edifices, writes regarding numerous issues concerning the Public Guard, the Armory, and the Virginia State Capitol. Dimmock writes regarding the cutting off of the supply of gas for the Capitol, Capitol Square, & the Bell House (1852 Jan. 15); the disposition of the engine or hose reel for the Capitol (1852 Feb. 15); an improvement in privy arrangements of the hospital for the Public Guard (1852 July 7); the request for chairs for the Auditor's Office (1852 July 13); muskets for Capt. McCandlish's Williamsburg Company (1852 Oct. 13); bed clothing for the hospital of the Public Guard (1852 Oct. 27); water from the canal to Braggs Mill under the West Wing of the Armory (1852 Nov. 7); a leak in the culvert which conveys water from the canal to the Armory building (1853 Apr. 18); printed proceedings of the Legislature (1853 Oct. 22); B. & S. Jones's proposal to supply rations to the Public Guard (1853 Sept. 26); carpets for the basement offices at the Capitol (1853 Oct. 20); the claim of Hilary Mosby (1853 Oct. 24); a list of articles necessary for the legal clothing of the Public Guard (1853 Dec. 14); authority to use the old carpets taken from the Capitol (1854 Jan. 3); a list of items needed for the use of the Armory Hospital (1854 Jan. 16); the sale of old stones on Capitol Square to B. B. Minor (1853 Feb. 23); the proposal to send the Armory Band to the Virginia Military Institute (1854 Mar. 7); relief from the Public Guard's duty of striking & ringing the state bell (1854 Apr. 8); the proposed street along the Armory grounds (1854 May 29); provisions for the Public Guard (1854 Sept. 27); an application of John T. Ford requesting the use of the Armory grounds for a balloon ascension during the Agricultural Fair (1854 Oct. 27); the claim of James Yarrington (1854 Nov. 13); Robert Archer's proposal to purchase arms from the state (1854 Dec. 8); the quantity of water used by the Commonwealth at the Armory (1855 Feb. 3); a new flag staff (1855 Feb. 16); the proposal of Stebbins & Mill to put up & repair lightning rods on the public buildings (1855 Mar. 8); bonds as security of the amount of rent of the State Boring Mill (1855 Mar. 26); compensation of the orderly for his services about the Capitol (1855 Apr. 18); the application of Private Dickenson of the Public Guard to have pay restored (1855 Mar. 31); repairs to furnaces in the Capitol (1855 Apr. 25); new coats & caps for the Public Guard (1855 May 14); repair of the culvert at the Armory (1855 June 13); the condition of the State Boring Mill (1855 Aug. 4); permission for the Public Guard to encamp elsewhere to avoid the yellow fever (1855 Aug. 12); proposals for furnishing rations to the Public Guard (1855 Sept. 25 & Oct. 2); and repairs to the Governor's House (1855 Oct. 2). Dimmock's 2nd-in-command, Lt. E. S. Gay writes regarding the stoppage of blasting work in constructing the street across from the public grounds at the Armory (1854 July 11).
  Charles S. Morgan, Superintendent of the Penitentiary, corresponded with Governor Johnson regarding various issues respecting prisoners and the Virginia Penitentiary. Morgan writes regarding the following topics: the number of transports remaining in the Penitentiary (1852 Feb. 28); Agnes, a pregnant convict in the Penitentiary (1852 June 16); a letter from Robert G. Scott, President of the Board of Directors, on behalf of Albert Burr who was sentenced to larceny in Richmond (1852 July 27); the record of Baker More, a free negro confined in the Penitentiary (1852 Dec. 2); the case of Norborne Crane, a free negro confined in the Penitentiary (1853 May 13); the price of tents made in the Penitentiary (1853 Aug. 18); an appropriation to appoint Simeon Grimsley as assistant keeper (1853 Sept. 8); the case of William H. Oney, a prisoner at the Penitentiary (1853 Dec. 23); the resolution regarding his recommendation for the pardon of S. A. Smith (1854 Feb. 11); the conduct of Alfred Dodd (1854 Feb. 23); transcripts of records in the cases of Wingfield Butcher & Robert Evans, free negroes in the Penitentiary (1854 Apr. 29); a case of small pox at the Penitentiary (1854 May 22); the removal of James Nesbitt as assistant keeper (1854 July 9); the appointment of John F. Meenly as assistant keeper of the Penitentiary (1854 Sept. 1); John McGalloway's bid for the purchase of four slaves confined in the Penitentiary (1854 Nov. 3); the conduct of William H. Scott, a free negro confined in the Penitentiary (1854 Nov. 24); the appointment of John Freeman as assistant keeper of the Penitentiary (1854 Nov. 27); records in the case of William B. Hooe (1854 Dec. 12); an estimate of the cost of repairing & rebuilding the Penitentiary shops destroyed by fire (incl. proceedings of the Board of Directors of the Penitentiary) (1854 Dec. 13); the conduct of John Bacchus, a convict in the Penitentiary (1855 Feb. 23); the fire at the Penitentiary and the re-construction & repair of the shops, machinery, etc. (1855 Feb. 16); the conduct of O. D. Clark, a convict in the Penitentiary (1855 Mar. 5); the resignation of Charles D. Moss as assistant keeper of the Penitentiary & the appointment of John M. Butler (1855 Mar. 2); the appointment of a 7th assistant keeper of the Penitentiary (1855 Mar. 26); the state of repairs to the Penitentiary and the sums expended thereon (1855 May 4); the case of John Smith, alias John S. Dumount (1855 May 16); the conduct of J. H. Blake, a convict in the Penitentiary (1855 May 14); and the conduct of James Donnally, a prisoner in the Penitentiary (1855 Nov. 7).
  Sidney Smith Baxter & Willis P. Bocock, Attorneys General, provided opinions regarding the following topics: a writ of election to fill the vacancy in the House of Delegates caused by the death of William C. Carrington (1852 Jan. 9); the demand of the governor of Pennsylvania for the delivery of Myer A. Levy (1852 Jan. 31); the demand of the governor of Maryland for E. T. Winder, a fugitive from justice (1852 May 4); the question of whether a court must be unanimous as to the question of quilt in order to sentence a slave to sale & transportation instead of death (1852 May 15); the elections in Loudoun County complained of by Sanford J. Ramey (1852 June 9); whether sheriffs ought to be commissioned to fill the offices of those whose offices by the old Constitution expire in March (1852 Dec. 16); the case of Lemmon, a slave, & Henry D. Lapaugh asking for compensation to be paid for printing records (1853 Mar. 14); the right of property in the value of slave Margaret condemned to death by the County Court of Culpeper (1853 Aug. 29); the bond of the treasurer and the question whether one inspector of tobacco can act during a vacancy in the offices of inspectors (1853 Aug. 25); the deed from the state to the United states government for several sites for lighthouses, beacons, etc. (1853 Sept. 30); the case of escheated land of John P. Dumas (1853 Dec. 16); the act of the Assembly passed on 25 February 1854 "authorizing the construction of a statue of Jefferson" (1854 June 30); and the proceedings of the officers of the 105th Regiment (1855 Oct. 9). On 1 November 1854, Bocock transmits his annual report as attorney general.
  George W. Munford, as Clerk of the House of Delegates, transmits the following certificates of election: Robert M. T. Hunter as senator (1852 Jan. 22); Robert Johnston as auditor, Robert Butler as Treasurer, George Munford as Secretary of the Commonwealth & Librarian, William L. Jackson as 2nd Auditor, Stafford H. Parker as Register of the Land Office, Charles S. Morgan as Superintendent of the Penitentiary, James C. Spotts as General Agent & Storekeeper, & William F. Ritchie as Public Printer (1852 Dec. 20); Brig. Gen. Thomas W. White of the 2nd Brigade of Militia in place of Gen. William Lambert, deceased (1853 Apr. 4); Jonathan B. Stovall as treasurer of the Commonwealth (1853 Aug. 3); and William Ritchie as Public Printer (1854 Mar. 28).
  In addition, Munford encloses several resolutions from the House of Delegates including a resolution of the House of Delegates that the Secretary of the Commonwealth be requested to report a list of all the slaves executed within each of the last five fiscal years, the owners, sum paid for each slave, etc. (1852 Feb. 6); a resolution of the House of Delegates that the governor be requested to inform the House what steps have been taken by him in pursuance to the resolution providing for causing casts of Houdon's Statue of Washington for colleges of the state (1852 Mar. 17); a resolution of the General Assembly that senators in Congress be instructed to procure the passage of a law making a further appropriation of scrip to satisfy Virginia military land bounty warrants (1852 Apr. 12); a resolution of the House that the executive furnish a tabular statement of the names & salaries of all the officers & agents of joint stock companies, of roads, bridges, & other institutions in which the state has an interest (1852 Mar. 27); and a resolution of the General Assembly accepting the act of Congress making further provision for the satisfaction of Virginia land warrants as a full & final adjustment of all bounty land claims to the officers & soldiers, seamen & marines of the state of Virginia for services in the war of the Revolution (1852 Dec. 9).
  Lastly, Munford writes Governor Johnson regarding the requisition upon the Executive of California for the surrender of Henry Banks, a fugitive slave (1853 Oct. 13). On 23 December 1853, Munford writes John Ward regarding a draft of Thomas Crawford for the bronze statues of Patrick Henry and the bas relief of Virginia for the Washington Equestrian Monument cast by Ferdinand von Miller at the Royal Foundry in Munich. Munford writes on the topic of the proposals of Robert Archer & Beverley Tucker to purchase public arms (1854 Dec. 21). Finally, Munford writes to Charles Dimmock regarding the repair of the front wall of the Boring Mill (1855 Aug. 17).
  Robert Johnston & George W. Clutter, Auditors of Public Accounts, correspond with Governor Johnson regarding various financial matters. Robert Johnston writes regarding the receipt of a bond of Garland P. Ware for the transportation of certain convict slaves & an agreement between the governor and R. Archer & Company for leasing a piece of ground belonging to the Armory (1852 Sept. 25); receipt for the bond of Robert Butler as treasurer (1853 Jan. 4); receipt for the bond of James C. Spotts as General Agent & Storekeeper of the Penitentiary (1853 Jan. 11); receipt for the bond of William Ritchie as Public Printer (1853 Jan. 20); an allowance for the claim of Samuel J. Repass for his services as drummer in the 86th Regiment (1853 Jan. 27); receipt for the bond of J. E. Shropshire & Edwin Walker for transporting a slave named Isaac (1853 Feb. 3); and money paid from the Literary Fund to the Virginia Military Institute library (1854 Jan. 20). As Johnston's replacement, George W. Clutter writes regarding his absence from office (1855 May 30); deficiencies in the Treasury (1855 June 13 & Nov. 22); and receipt of bonds for the sale of convict slaves sold from the Penitentiary (1855 July 9).
  Governors and secretaries from other states comprise a significant amount of correspondence received by the Governor. This correspondence mostly relates to the extradition of fugitives. Included are letters from the following governors or secretaries: Enoch L. Lowe & Thomas W. Ligon, Maryland; William Bigler & James Pollock, Pennsylvania; John Hubbard, Maine; Reuben Wood & William Medill, Ohio; Horatio Seymour, Elias W. Leavenworth, & Myron H. Clark, New York; William H. Ross, Delaware; David S. Reid, North Carolina; Howell Cobb, Georgia; Noah Martin, New Hampshire; John A. Winston, Alabama; Oliver H. Perry, Connecticut; Lazarus W. Powell, Kentucky; and John H. Clifford & Henry J. Gardner, Massachusetts.